# **AKHILA ATMAKURU**

# Researcher | Data Scientist | Scrum Master

London, UK | <u>Akhila\_LinkedIn</u> | Akhila\_Github\_Portfolio | <u>akhila.atmakuru11@gmail.com</u> | +44-(0)7918358129

#### **PROFILE SUMMARY**

Experienced PhD Graduate and detail-oriented researcher with strong programming skills in creating and implementing predictive models to solve complex real-world challenges. Experienced in Market Research, Stakeholder Management, Leadership, Risk Management, and Financial Management. Acknowledged for adeptly overseeing and organizing research projects throughout a six-year tenure. I am currently in the final year of my PhD, specializing in Artificial Intelligence for Computational Neuroscience. My research focuses on developing explainable deep-learning models for predicting neurodegenerative diseases. I anticipate graduating in September 2024.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

**A. Atmakuru et al.** "Sensitivity Analysis for Feature Importance in Predicting Alzheimer's Disease" ACAIN 2023, LNCS, Springer, 2024

**A. Atmakuru et al.** "Improved Filter-Based Feature Selection Using Correlation and Clustering Techniques" LOD 2023, LNCS, Springer, 2024.

**Co-author.** "Classification-Biased Apparent Brain Age for the Prediction of Alzheimer's Disease" Frontiers in Neuroscience, 2021.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

### **Certification:**

- ✓ Professional Scrum Master -1 Certification from Scrum Organization (Scrum.org).
- ✓ Amazon Web Services Solution Architect.

#### **Technical Skills:**

- C, C++, R, and Python
- Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch
- Scikit Learn, Pandas, NumPy & Matplotlib
- Data visualization Tableau, PowerBI
- Computer Vision, Timeseries Analysis & NLP
- Confluence & Jira, Trello

#### **AWARDS**

- Outstanding performance Award in Post-Graduation for achieving excellence at Cranfield University.
- "Star of the Team" Award for developing a scalable computer vision project "Intelligent Rail Monitor".

### **EDUCATION**

### **Doctorate in Artificial Intelligence**

Oct 2021 - Sep 2024

University of Reading

Reading, UK

Thesis Topic: Research is focused on advancing AI for Healthcare by addressing key challenges in predicting early Neuro-Degenerative Diseases (NDDs), improving the interpretability of Deep Learning models, and optimizing Multi-Task Learning (MTL). Two conference papers have been published on Feature Selection and Sensitivity Analysis, which leverage a diverse dataset of structural MRI scans encompassing six major NDDs as well as healthy subjects. Additionally, methods are currently being developed to predict the stages of NDDs. This research contributes to the development of AI methodologies for healthcare applications, with a particular emphasis on NDD prediction and model explainability.

# **Masters in Applied Artificial Intelligence**

**Sep 2020** 

Cranfield University Cranfield, UK

**Thesis Topic:** Artificial Intelligence techniques suitable for UAV-based surveillance systems. The AI techniques have been developed for the identification of three species of sharks, tracking the shark movements, and classification of aggressive and non-aggressive sharks based on the pattern of their swimming movements. The AI software algorithms have been trained on a Medium-sized dataset created using videos available in the public domain. The dataset is subjected to suitable filtering and augmentation procedures to enhance the performance of subsequent processing steps. The results obtained from the algorithms show satisfactory results in classifying different species of sharks and tracking aggressive and non - aggressive behaviors.

### **EXPERIENCE**

# **Department of Computer Science, UNIVERSITY OF READING:**

Oct 2020 - Sep 2021

### **Researcher & Teaching Fellow:**

- Published novel methods for early prediction of Alzheimer's using Deep Learning models.
- Other Research Activities: Data Visualization, FreeSurfer for Pre-processing medical Image datasets.
- Courses Taught: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Data Visualization, Operating Systems, and Python.

### **TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES:**

Mar 2016 - Sep 2019

#### Scrum Master & Senior Data Scientist:

Central R&D Team, Chennai, India

Nov 2018 - Sep 2019

- Successfully developed models for computer vision, time series analysis, natural language processing, and recommendation systems.
- Led sprint planning, sprint reviews, sprint retrospectives, and daily scrums resulting in the successful delivery of major projects in the group.
- Worked closely with the Product Owner in managing customer expectations and backlog management.

### **Data Scientist:**

Central R&D Team, Chennai, India

Mar 2016 - Oct 2018

- Developed and deployed predictive language models for chatbots tailored for Human Resources applications.
- Delivered Data visualization models using PowerBI/Tableau to clients for effective trend analysis.